Ben Johnson Papers
Ben Johnson Papers
1951-1968
Johnson, Ben, 1902-1967
4.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American painter. Spanning 1951 to 1968, the Ben Johnson Papers comprises correspondence, artwork, writings, and memorabilia of the Brooklyn-born painter (1902-1967) who specialized in female nude figures. Illuminating Johnson's personal and professional life, the collection also provides insight into the career of his wife, artist Alice Terry (b. 1925). Includes correspondence, personal and business, including family letters (1951-1968); photographs of Johnson's paintings; interviews, statements on art; lists of paintings, partially annotated with prices; and printed material, including articles and reviews (1963-1967), newspaper clippings (1954-1967), and exhibition catalogs and invitations (1962-1966).
149084
Biographical History
Ben Johnson (1902-1967) was a Brooklyn-born painter who specialized in female nude figures.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Spanning 1951 to 1968, the Ben Johnson Papers comprises correspondence, artwork, writings, and memorabilia of the Brooklyn-born painter (1902-1967) who specialized in female nude figures. Illuminating Johnson's personal and professional life, the collection also provides insight into the career of his wife, artist Alice Terry (b. 1925). Includes correspondence, personal and business, including family letters (1951-1968); photographs of Johnson's paintings; interviews, statements on art; lists of paintings, partially annotated with prices; and printed material, including articles and reviews (1963-1967), newspaper clippings (1954-1967), and exhibition catalogs and invitations (1962-1966).
Family correspondence (Box 1) from Alice Terry's relatives predominates, however there are also a significant number of letters between Ben Johnson and his wife, as well as some from their children. Additional family material other than correspondence may be found in Memorabilia.
Correspondence-subject files (Boxes 2-7), primarily from the 1960s, consists of incoming and outgoing letters and carbons, as well as other documents relating to the artwork of both Johnson and Terry. Unless otherwise noted, the remainder of the collection pertains to Johnson only. Fellow artists are among the correspondents listed (Helen Avlon-Daphnis, Will Barnet, Robert Bero, Henry Billings, Frank Colson, John W, Dixon, Guy Owen Dolen, Bruce Dorfman, Jim Eakle, Emmet Edwards,Nancy Ellison, Dan Fruits, Sandy Goodman, Bruce Gregory, Philip Held, Klindt Houlberg, Bob Jacobson, Tom Keating, Gabriel Kohn, Joseph Konzal, Ethel Kott, Eleanore Lockspeiser, Jack Lubin, Robert R. Malone, Hugh Mesibov, Morris C. Mitchell, Lyn Ott, Fairfield Porter, Craig Rubadoux, Dolores Ryan, Edward G. Samuels, Walter Schramm, Richard Segalman, Stuart Van Orden, Richard Wagner, William Walmsley, George M. Wardlaw, William Weiner, George Wexler, Julia Papiroff Zagar). Other correspondents include authors and critics (Jacqueline Barnitz, Rosalind Browne, Lawrence Campbell, John Canaday, John Ciardi, Gerald H. Dorset, John Gruen, Ben M. Hall, Beth Hannah, Nina Kaiden, Anthony Kerrigan, Hilton Kramer, Margaret Rigg, Sheldon Williams, Miriam Young); patrons and notable admirers (Joseph James Akston, William Benton, Tony Curtis, Frederick C. Gans, Arthur and Carol Goldberg, James E. Hanson, Arthur L. Harris, Carl Hertzberg, Louis and Margaret Kannenstine, Miriam Kazon, Richard and Gloria Kins, Monique Knowlton, George Frederick Morgan, Paul Jacques Schupf, Martin T. Sosnoff, John C. Stetson, Billy Wilder); photographers (Robin Johnstone, Herb Snitzer); and poets (John Lucas, Selden Rodman). The couple's involvement with Christian Science is documented in their correspondence with Harold and Virginia Marietta.
Organizational correspondence includes that with art associations (American Federation of Arts, Associated American Artists, Christian Art Associates, Woodstock Artists Association); art galleries and museums (Baltimore Museum of Art, Banfer Gallery, Byron Gallery, Collectors Gallery, Findlay Galleries, Flair Gallery, Rose Fried Gallery, Gallery Dache, Gallery 63, Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum, I Gallery, Kornblee Gallery, Joe and Emily Lowe Art Gallery, Museum of Modern Art, Pace Gallery, Lillian Phipps Gallery, Rosequist Galleries, Selected Artists Galleries, David Stuart Galleries, Vancouver Art Gallery, Visual Artists Gallery, Whitney Museum of American Art, Howard Wise Gallery); educational institutions (Florida State University, Purdue University, Syracuse University); and periodicals and publishers (Allied Publications, Art Voices, Arts Magazine, Playboy, Wittenborn and Company).
Photographs of Johnson's paintings, alphabetized by title when provided, constitute Artwork (Box 8). Writings (Box 8) consists of interviews via mail and radio, statements on art, and miscellaneous notes.
Memorabilia (Boxes 8 and 9) encompasses addresses, an exhibition quest register, lists of paintings partially annotated with prices, a paintbrush and mixing dish, photographs of Johnson and family, political and religious material, press releases of exhibitions, artwork and memorabilia of Alice Terry, travel an tourism information, and printed material. Printed material includes articles and reviews abot Johnson (1963-1967), newspaper clippings (1954-1967), exhibition catalogs and invitations including Johnson's work (1962-1966), as well as posters for two exhibitions.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by sender. Material within the other series is arranged alphabetically by title or topic.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Barnet, Will, 1911-2012.; Billings, Henry, 1901-; Campbell, Lawrence, 1914-1998.; Canaday, John, 1907-1985.; Ciardi, John, 1916-1986.; Curtis, Tony, 1925-2010.; Dorfman, Bruce, 1936-; Dixon, John W., Jr., 1919-2004.; Ellison, Nancy.; Fruits, Dan.; Gruen, John.; Hall, Ben M.; Hannah, Beth H.; Johnson, Ben, 1902-1967.; Kaiden, Nina N.; Kannenstine, Louis F., 1938-; Keating, Tom, 1917-; Kerrigan, Anthony.; Kohn, Gabriel, 1910-1975.; Konzal, Joseph.; Kramer, Hilton.; Ott, Lyn.; Porter, Fairfield.; Rigg, Margaret.; Rodman, Selden, 1909-2002.; Schupf, Paul Jacques.; Segalman, Richard.; Snitzer, Herb.; Sosnoff, Martin T.; Sturgeon, Theodore.; Terry, Alice.; Wardlaw, George M., 1927-; Wilder, Billy, 1906-2002.; Young, Miriam, 1913-; Art, American.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Figure painting.; Human figure in art.; Nude in art.; Painters -- United States.; Painting, American.; Painting, American -- 20th century.; Women in art.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Exhibition catalogs.; Interviews.; Photographs.; Artists.; Painters.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Family Correspondence
  - Axel, Leon (Alice Terry's son), 1964-1968 (Box 1)
  - Hertz Family (Alice Terry's sister's family), 1966-1967; undated (Box 1)
  - Johnson, Ben and Susan (Alice Terry and Ben Johnson's children), undated
    See also Memorabilia: Family.
  - Johnston, B. F. (Mr. & Mrs. - Ben Johnson's parents), 1952-1954; undated (Box 1)
  - Terry, Alice (wife of Ben Johnson; to and from Ben Johnson), 1951-1966; undated (Box 1)
  - Terry, Leon and Rose (Alice Terry's parents), 1955; 1963-1967,; undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Correspondence-Subject Files
  - Abrams, Harry N., 1965 (Box 2)
  - Adams Purchasing Company (New York, N.Y.), See Kins, Richard and Gloria.
  - Akston, Joseph James, 1964-1967 (Box 2)
  - Allied Publications, Inc. (Fort Lauderdale, Fla.), 1965 (Box 2)
  - American Federation of Arts, 1963-1968; undated (Box 2)
  - Angeloch, Nancy, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Armstrong, Roseann, 1964-1967; undated (Box 2)
  - Art Voices, 1964-1965 (Box 2)
    See also Akston, Joseph James; Barnitz, Jacqueline.
  - Arts Magazine, 1963-1967 (Box 2)
  - Associated American Artists (New York, N.Y.), 1965-1966 (Box 2)
  - Avlon-Daphnis, Helen, 1963-1966; undated (Box 2)
  - [N. W.] Ayer & Son (Philadelphia, Pa.), 1964-1965 (Box 2)
  - Baltimore Museum of Art, undated (Box 2)
  - Banfer Gallery (New York, N.Y.), 1963-1964 (Box 2)
  - Barnet, Will, 1965-1967 (Box 2)
  - Barnitz, Jacqueline, 1965; 1967 (Box 2)
  - Benton, William, 1964-1965 (Box 2)
  - Bero, Robert, 1963-1965 (Box 2)
  - Billings, Henry, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Bocour Artist Colors Incorporated (New York, N.Y.), 1963 (Box 2)
  - Bosch, Gulnar K., See Florida State University.
  - Browne, Rosalind, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Bush, Martin H., See Syracuse University.
  - Byron Gallery, Inc. (New York, N.Y.), 1964-1965 (Box 2)
  - Campbell, Lawrence, 1965-1966 (Box 2)
  - Canaday, John, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Carroll, Vega, Brown and Nichols (Naples, Fla.), 1968 (Box 2)
  - Christian Art Associates (Chicago, Ill.), 1967-1968 (Box 2)
  - Ciardi, John, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Collectors Gallery, Inc. (Miami, Fla.), 1965 (Box 2)
  - Colson, Frank, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Craft, John Richard, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Curtis, Tony, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Dache, Lily, See Gallery Dache.
  - Dain-Schiff Picture Framers Inc. (New York, N.Y.), 1964-1966 (Box 2)
  - Daphnis, Helen, See Avlon-Daphnis, Helen.
  - Dixon, John W., 1963-1967; undated (Box 2)
  - Dolen, Guy Owen, 1966-1968; undated (Box 2)
  - Dorfman, Bruce and Jeanne, 1965-1967 (Box 2)
  - Dorset, Gerald H., 1964 (Box 2)
    See also Gallery 63.
  - Doyle, Richard P., 1963-1965 (Box 2)
  - Eakle, Jim, 1963-1967; undated (Box 3)
  - Edwards, Emmet, 1954; 1964 (Box 3)
  - Ellison, Nancy, undated (Box 3)
  - Englewood Armory Art Show, 1964-1965 (Box 3)
  - Ernst, Pearl Bond, 1964 (Box 3)
  - Findlay Galleries Inc. (Palm Beach, Fla.), 1965 (Box 3)
  - Flair Gallery (Cincinnati, Ohio), 1968 (Box 3)
  - Florida State University, 1965-1967 (Box 3)
  - [Rose] Fried Gallery (New York, N.Y.), 1963-1964 (Box 3)
  - Fruits, Dan, 1964-1967 (Box 3)
  - Gallery Dache (New York, N.Y.), 1964-1968; undated (Box 3)
  - Gallery 63 (New York, N.Y.), 1964-1965; undated (Box 3)
  - Gans, Frederick C., 1965; 1966 (Box 3)
  - Goldberg, Arthur and Carol, 1966 (Box 3)
  - Goodman, Sandy, 1963 (Box 3)
  - [Max] Granick, Frames, 1963-1964 (Box 3)
  - Gregory, Bruce and Millie, 1963-1967 (Box 3)
  - Gruen, John, 1966-1967 (Box 3)
  - [Solomon R.] Guggenheim Museum, 1963 (Box 3)
  - Hall, Ben M., 1963; 1964 (Box 3)
  - Hamilton, Frank, 1964; 1967 (Box 3)
  - Hannah, Beth, 1967-1968 (Box 3)
  - Hanson, James E., 1965-1966 (Box 3)
  - Harris, Arthur L. and Liliane, 1964-1967 (Box 4)
  - Hartman, Ferris and Iris, 1955; 1964,; 1967 (Box 4)
  - Held, Philip and Ann, 1963-1968; undated (Box 4)
  - Hertzberg, Carl, 1966 (Box 4)
  - Hessler, Janie, 1965; undated (Box 4)
  - Higgins, Gretchen, 1963; 1964,; undated (Box 4)
  - Houlberg, Klindt, 1965-1966
    See also Purdue University.
  - I Gallery (La Jolla, Calif.), 1963 (Box 4)
  - Jacobson, Bob, 1962-1963; undated (Box 4)
  - Johnstone, Robin, 1968 (Box 4)
  - Junior Council of the Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.), See Museum of Modern Art. (Box 4)
  - Kaiden, Nina, 1965-1967 (Box 4)
  - Kannenstine, Louis F. and Margaret L., 1965-1967; undated (Box 4)
  - Kazon, Miriam, 1964-1967 (Box 4)
  - Kazon, Philip, 1965 (Box 4)
  - Keating, Tom, 1963-1968; undated (Box 4)
  - Kerrigan, Anthony, 1963 (Box 4)
  - Kins, Richard and Gloria, 1964-1966; undated (Box 4)
  - Knowlton, Monique, 1965-1967; undated (Box 4)
  - Kohn, Gabriel, 1963; 1967 (Box 4)
  - Konzal, Joseph, 1962-1963 (Box 4)
  - Kornblee Gallery (New York, N.Y.), 1962; 1963,; undated (Box 4)
  - Kott, Ethel and Seymour, 1964-1968 (Box 4)
  - Kramer, Hilton, 1962-1967 (Box 4)
  - Lockspeiser, Eleanore, 1963 (Box 4)
  - [Joe and Emily] Lowe Art Gallery (Coral Gables, Fla.), 1965-1968 (Box 4)
  - Lubin, Jack, 1962-1968; undated (Box 4)
  - Lucas, John, 1966 (Box 4)
  - Malone, Robert R., 1965-1967; undated (Box 5)
  - Mann, Charles Z., 1963 (Box 5)
  - Marietta, Harold E. and Virginia, 1962-1968; undated; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Mesibov, Hugh, 1964 (Box 5)
  - Mitchell, Morris C., 1963-1967 (Box 5)
  - Morgan, George Frederick, 1965-1966 (Box 5)
  - Moscowitz, Alvin E., 1963-1966; undated (Box 5)
  - Multiples, Inc. (New York, N.Y.), 1965-1966 (Box 5)
  - Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.), 1955; 1963 (Box 5)
  - National Council of Jewish Women, See Englewood Armory Art Show.
  - Orr, David, 1962-1963 (Box 5)
  - Ott, Lyn, 1955; 1965 (Box 5)
  - Pace Gallery (New York, N.Y.), 1964 (Box 5)
  - [Lillian] Phipps Gallery, Inc. (Palm Beach, Fla.), 1966 (Box 5)
  - Playboy, 1966-1967 (Box 5)
  - Porter, Fairfield, 1956 (Box 5)
  - Primoff, Morris W., 1965-1967; undated; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Purdue University (Lafayette, Ind.), 1965-1966 (Box 5)
  - Rigg, Margaret, 1963; 1964,; 1968,; undated (Box 6)
  - Rodman, Selden, 1960-1963; undated (Box 6)
  - Rosequist Galleries (Tucson, Ariz.), 1965-1966 (Box 6)
  - Rubadoux, Craig, 1961; 1965-1968,; undated (Box 6)
  - Ruder & Finn Incorporated (New York, N.Y.), 1964-1966 (Box 6)
  - Ryan, Dolores, 1966-1967 (Box 6)
  - Samuels, Edward G., 1962-1965 (Box 6)
  - Saratoga Thoroughbred Racing Centennial, Inc. (Saratoga Springs, N.Y.), 1963 (Box 6)
  - Schramm, Walter, 1964; 1965 (Box 6)
  - Schupf, Paul Jacques, 1966 (Box 6)
  - Segalman, Richard, 1966; undated (Box 6)
  - Selected Artists Galleries Inc. (New York, N.Y.), 1965; 1966 (Box 6)
  - Snitzer, Herb, 1962-1964 (Box 6)
  - Sosnoff, Martin T., 1957; 1966-1967 (Box 6)
  - Stetson, John C., 1964-1965 (Box 6)
  - [David] Stuart Galleries (Los Angeles, Calif.), 1963-1965; undated (Box 6)
  - Sturgeon, Theodore, 1963 (Box 6)
  - Syracuse University, 1964-1967 (Box 6)
  - Terry, Alice, See Family Correspondence: Terry, Alice, Memorabilia: Terry, Alice.
  - University of Miami, See [Joe and Emily] Lowe Art Gallery.
  - Van Orden, Stuart C., 1966 (Box 6)
  - Vancouver Art Gallery, 1964-1965 (Box 6)
  - Vincent, Richard, 1966 (Box 6)
  - Visual Arts Gallery (New York, N.Y.), 1966-1967 (Box 6)
  - Wagner, Richard and Evelyn, 1966; 1967,; undated (Box 7)
  - Walmsley, William, 1965; 1966 (Box 7)
    See also Florida State University.
  - Wardlaw, George M., 1963-1966 (Box 7)
  - Weiner, William A. and Sue Ellen, 1963-1967; undated; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Wexler, George, 1963-1967; undated (Box 7)
  - Whitney Museum of American Art (New York, N.Y.), 1963-1966; undated (Box 7)
  - Wilder, Billy, 1964-1966 (Box 7)
  - Williams, Sheldon, 1967 (Box 7)
  - [Howard] Wise Gallery (New York, N.Y.), 1963; 1965 (Box 7)
  - Wittenborn and Company (New York, N.Y.), 1965; undated (Box 7)
  - Woodstock Artists Association, 1956-1966; undated (Box 7)
  - Young, Miriam and Walter, 1964-1967 (Box 7)
  - Zagar, Julia Papiroff and Irwin, 1965 (Box 7)
- Artwork
  - Photographs
    - Titled (A-Z) (Box 8)
    - Untitled (Box 8)
- Writings
  - Interviews, 1964; 1965,; undated (Box 8)
  - Statements on art, 1966; undated (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 8)
- Memorabilia
  - Addresses (Box 8)
  - Calling cards (Box 8)
  - Family (Box 8)
  - Guest register, exhibition, 1965 (Box 8)
  - Lists of paintings (partially annotated with prices) (Box 8)
  - Paintbrush, mixing dish, key (Box 9)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 9)
  - Political/religious (Box 9)
  - Press releases, 1954; 1963,; 1965,; undated (Box 9)
  - Printed material
    - Articles, reviews, 1963-1967; undated (Box 9)
    - Clippings, 1954-1967; undated (Box 9)
    - Exhibition catalogs, invitations, 1962-1966; undated (Box 9)
    - Exhibition posters, 1963; undated (Box 9)
    - Exhibition catalogs, invitations (non-Johnson), 1961-1967; undated (Box 9)
    - Periodicals, 1964-1966; undated; Iris.Time and other Iris Clert mailings (Box 9)
  - Terry, Alice, artwork and memorabilia (Box 9)
  - Travel, tourism (Box 9)
  - Miscellany (Box 9)